Arthur B. Poinier Cartoons
Arthur B. Poinier Cartoons
1952-1968
1960-1968
Poinier, Arthur.
12.5 linear ft.
Over 2,000 original editorial cartoons drawn for the Detroit News.
149525
Biographical History
Art Poinier (1911-1998) was an American editorial cartoonist.
Arthur B. "Art" Poinier was born February 9, 1911. He received a B.A. from Ohio Wesleyan in 1932 and while in college he drew sports cartoons for the Columbus Dispatch. During the Great Depression, Poinier worked for the Cleveland Press. After being laid off, in 1934, he moved to Iowa to work as a staff artist for the Des Moines Register and Tribune from 1934 to 1936. During World War II, Poinier served with the United States Navy as an air combat intelligence officer.
In 1939, Poinier joined the staff of the Detroit Free Press. In 1951 he left that position to be the editorial cartoonist for the Detroit News. During his career, his work was distributed by the Bell Syndicate and Associated Newspapers. He also drew the Jitter strip from 1936 to 1943, whose title character was a rambunctious chimpanzee.
Poinier was a member of the National Cartoonists Society and at one time president of the American Association of Editorial Cartoonists. His work appeared in the annual compilation Best Editorial Cartoons of the Year. He received eight awards from the Freedoms Foundation while with the Detroit News, including one for a cartoon that was critical of the Vietnam War. He was also a member of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP).
Poinier was also a farmer and grew apples on his farm. He retired in 1976 and died on May 4, 1998 in Lexington, Kentucky.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Arthur B. Poinier Cartoons consist of editorial cartoons published in the Detroit News from 1952 to 1968. The majority of the cartoons are from the 1960s; years 1952-1959 are housed in a single box.
The single series Cartoons consists of approximately 2,211 original editorial cartoons as well as 13 proofs and reproductions. Poinier often produced several cartoons for each day. Some are labeled "alternate" or "extra". Of particular interest is a cartoon drawn following the shooting of Robert F. Kennedy that depicts him entering heaven. The cartoon, drawn in advance of Kennedy's passing is labeled to only be used in the event of his death.
Cartoons vary in size; however the majority measure 14" x 22 1/2". Poinier worked in ink and crayon; other materials include whiteout. Traces of pencil are visible and captions are written in ink.
Arrangement of the Collection
Items are arranged chronologically. Proofs are filed in with original artwork. At the end of most years there is at least one folder of cartoons from that year that are marked "extra" or "alternate" and do not have specific dates.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Poinier, Arthur.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Detroit News Company.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Caricatures and cartoons -- Michigan -- Detroit.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Cartoonists -- Michigan -- Detroit.; Editorial cartoons -- Michigan -- Detroit.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; World politics -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Proofs (printed matter); Editorial cartoons.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Arthur B. Poinier, 1967-1968.
Inventory
- Cartoons, Click here for a detailed inventory.
  - 1952-1959 (Oversize 1)
  - 1960 Jan-Dec (Oversize 2)
  - 1960, 1961 Jan-May (Oversize 3)
  - 1961 Jun-Dec (Oversize 4)
  - 1961, 1962 Jan-May (Oversize 5)
  - 1962 Jun-Nov (Oversize 6)
  - 1962, 1962 Dec-1963 Apr (Oversize 7)
  - 1963 May-Dec (Oversize 8)
  - 1963, 1964 Jan-Aug (Oversize 9)
  - 1964 Sep-Dec, 1964 (Oversize 10)
  - 1965 Jan-Aug (Oversize 11)
  - 1965 Sep-Dec, 1965 (Oversize 12)
  - 1966 Jan-Jun (Oversize 13)
  - 1966 Jul-Dec, 1966 (Oversize 14)
  - 1967 Jan-Jun (Oversize 15)
  - 1967 Jul-Oct, 1967 (Oversize 16)
  - 1968 Sep-Nov, 1968 (Oversize 17)
  - 1968 (Oversize 18)
  - 1968 (Oversize 19)